<aiml version="1.0.1" encoding="UTF-8">
    <category>
        <pattern>^ HELLO ^</pattern>
        <template>
            <random>
                <li>Hello! Ask me some questions.</li>
                <li>Hi! Ask me some questions.</li>
                <li>Ask me some questions!</li>
            </random>
        </template>
    </category>

    <category>
        <pattern>Give me welcome message</pattern>

        <template>Hello, my name is John and I'm your friendly bot. You can ask me questions about diabetes.</template>
    </category>

    <category>
        <pattern>^ HI ^</pattern>

        <template><srai>^ hello ^</srai></template>
    </category>

    <!-- food and drinks -->
    <category>
        <pattern>^ ALCOHOL ^</pattern>
        <template>
            Alcohol can raise and lower sugar levels depending on amounts and types.
            Moderate amounts of alcohol may increase levels, especially if they are higher carbohydrate drinks such as beer or sweeter mixed drinks.
            Too much alcohol can cause low blood sugar.
        </template>
    </category>

    <category>
        <pattern>^ SKIPPING LUNCH ^</pattern>
        <template>
            Skipping meals can send glucose levels on a bit of a roller coaster ride.
            The liver can actually release too much glucose into the bloodstream when no food has been eaten.
            You should rather eat regular smaller meals with lower carb/healthy foods.
        </template>
    </category>

    <category>
        <pattern>^ SKIPPING MEALS ^</pattern>
        <template><srai>^ skipping lunch ^</srai></template>
    </category>

    <category>
        <pattern>^ SKIPPING DINNER ^</pattern>
        <template><srai>^ skipping lunch ^</srai></template>
    </category>

    <category>
        <pattern>^ SKIPPING BREAKFAST ^</pattern>
        <template><srai>^ skipping lunch ^</srai></template>
    </category>

    <category>
        <pattern>^ REGULAR MEALS ^</pattern>
        <template><srai>^ skipping lunch ^</srai></template>
    </category>

    <category>
        <pattern>^ JUICING ^</pattern>
        <template>
            You may be raising your levels with too much juice, especially if you are using lots of fruit.
            Even though fruit juice is high in vitamins, it is still sugar to the body and challenges insulin output.
            You should check your blood sugar levels for a time to see how your current juices are affecting your levels.
        </template>
    </category>

    <category>
        <pattern>^ PROTEIN ^</pattern>
        <template>
            You should eat around 0.8 - 1.0 gm of protein for each kg of body weight. Body builders and elite athletes may require more.
            Your main dietary focus should be unrefined foods, lots of veggies, and fish.
        </template>
    </category>

    <category>
        <pattern>^ SWEETENER ^</pattern>
        <template>
            The sweetener of choice for many is Stevia. It is 200 times sweeter than sucrose and can be used in cooking.
            In addition to its sweetening property, Stevia has been shown to lower both blood pressure and blood sugar levels in animal studies.
            Also, it is packaged under more than one name, and is available in both liquid and powder forms.
        </template>
    </category>

    <category>
        <pattern>^ STEVIA ^</pattern>
        <template><srai>^ sweetener ^</srai></template>
    </category>

    <category>
        <pattern>^ SUGAR SUBSTITUTE ^</pattern>
        <template><srai>^ sweetener ^</srai></template>
    </category>

    <!-- general questions -->
    <category>
        <pattern>How to recognize diabetes</pattern>
        <template>
            Some of the symptoms of diabetes are frequent and copious urination, dry mouth, excessive thirst,
            lack of energy, weight loss or gain, slow wound healing or frequent infections, fruit odor.
        </template>
    </category>

    <category>
        <pattern>^ SYMPTOMS ^</pattern>
        <template><srai>How to recognize diabetes</srai></template>
    </category>

    <category>
        <pattern>Can stress increase blood sugar levels</pattern>
        <template>
            Stress can elevate blood sugar, and if you are already requiring insulin when you are otherwise unstressed,
            you may need more at these times.
        </template>
    </category>

    <category>
        <pattern>Can being sick increase blood sugar</pattern>
        <template>
            Illness can lead to an increase in blood sugar levels. The most important step to take during illness
            is to make sure that blood sugar levels are stable to prevent a small problem like a cold or the flu
            from causing greater problems.
        </template>
    </category>
</aiml>